Guide to the Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Photographs PHOTOS.013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Photographs
Bulk, 1957-1970
1938-1981, (Bulk 1957-1970)
PHOTOS.013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
3.25 linear feet (ca. 3,800 items; 148 folders), 8x10; b&w.
The Central Union Label Council of New York City (later the Union Label and Services Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island) was founded to promote union-labeled goods and union-made products, through lobbying, service and publicity. Chartered by the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor in 1911, in its early years the Council established and ran a department store stocked with union-made products. By the 1950s, promotion took the form of mounting annual labor-management trade shows, "Miss Union Maid" beauty contests, sponsoring a weekly labor press radio program, and other public relations efforts. The collection consists of ca. 3,800 images that span the late 1930s through the early 1980s, with the bulk from 1957-1970. The majority are 8x10 black and white copy prints shot by a variety of commercial photographers. More than half document annual conventions of the New York State Union Label Trades and the conventions’ associated activities. Prints of special historic interest include images of the 1938 Union Label Week parade in New York City; a mass rally at Madison Square Garden opposing the Taft-Hartley Act, and comely young women used to advertise the Council’s agenda.
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island sent a gift of their records in 1986. Photographs from that collection were separated and established as the Union Label and Service Trades Council of Grater New York and Long Island Photographs. The accession number associated with this collection is 1986.031.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1911, the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor chartered the Central Union Label Council of New York City. Like its parent body, which had been established by Samuel Gompers in 1909, the New York City Label Council was dedicated to "a more systematic and thorough agitation and demand for union-made and particularly union label products, and for the patronage of union organizations issuing them." In 1916, the Council sold stock to establish a department store of union label products, which it then ran and stocked. After World War II, the increasing number of retail stores carrying union-made products greatly increased, prompting the Council to close its store in 1947.
The Label Council, and later its state counterpart, focused on lobbying, service and publicity, all in the interest of union-labeled goods produced by members of craft unions. Although separate central bodies existed in Manhattan and Brooklyn in 1911, the Central Union Label Council, headquartered in Brooklyn in its own building at 902-4 Broadway, bridged the boroughs. Charles Sinnigen, a member of the Electrotypers Local 100, served as the Council's Secretary. In 1935, the Union Label Trades and Services Department of the AFL chartered a Union Label Trades and Services Department for the state of New York. The organization moved to Bible House, where Charles Sinnigen directed both the city and the state organization as Secretary-Treasurer. The state organization called conventions annually and published the Union Label News.
After Sinnigen's death in 1949, Harry Avrutin, formerly an organizer for the Office and Professional Employees International Union, was elected Secretary-Treasurer of the Union Label and Services Trades Council of Greater New York. Placing greater emphasis on publicity tactics, Avrutin published annual buyers' guides to union-made products, mounted labor-management trade shows during "Union Label Week" (the first week of September), staged a"Miss Union Maid" beauty contest, sponsored a weekly Labor Press radio program, and engaged in other public relations efforts designed to promote union labor and products, and, increasingly, to encourage unionized business to remain in the metropolitan area. In 1959, the New York Council expanded its jurisdiction to Nassau and Suffolk Counties.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection is 8x10 black and white copy prints. The images were shot by a variety of commercial photographers, but Alexander Archer and his studio are particularly well-represented. There is some overlap between the contents of the images in the different topical series.
More than half the images in the collection document the annual conventions of the New York State Union Label Trades and the conventions' associated activities, including an annual trade show of products and services produced in union shops (variously known as the Labor-Management Show, Empire State Labor-Management Show, Labor and Management Exhibit, Union Industry Show, and Union Label Exhibit), Union Label Week, and a Miss Union Maid contest. (Photocopied) clippings from scrapbooks of newsprint material provide additional background material on the conventions and activities sponsored by the Council. The convention shots focus on displays of union-made goods, of portraits of Council leadership, and the Miss Union Maid contestants and winners. Miss Union Maid and other women union members are shown in decorative poses, and modeling furs and stockings (and in one instance, a long rope of frankfurters around the neck). Also shown are performances (some of them colorful) at the trade show--from trick dogs and sheep-shearing (the latter with Governor Nelson Rockefeller in attendance), to live music with chanteuses.
Several prints are of special historic interest. These include images of the 1938 Union Label Week parade in New York City; a mass rally at Madison Square Garden with placards urging the President to "Veto the Taft-Hartley Slave Labor Bill"; the Bookkeepers, Stenographers and Accountant Union of the AFL staging a comical demonstration (in the 1930s) to organize office workers ("You have nothing to lose - organize," proclaim the placards of barrel-clad--and wearing nothing else--picketers); and a Cold War-era comparison of controlled and free enterprise, based on how many hours American workers versus workers in the Soviet Union work to pay for a suit and other commodities ("How Much Ivan Pays/How Much We Pay"). Other highlights include: images of "Little Miss Union Maid," the little girl who was also the Muscular Dystrophy Association "poster child" that year, being welcomed to the 1969 convention; a "Miss Union Label" (ca.1950s) wearing a scanty costume and remarkable headgear and posed perching on the bar of a union establishment (a sign confirms it); and a small series of workplace images ranging from the 1940s to the 1970s of butchers (Butcher's Union Local 174) and glaziers at work, and a bottling plant. Persons specifically pictured include: Harry Avrutin, Isidore Becker, Reverend Phillip A. Carey, Edward Cleary, Bertha J. Diggs, Nicholas Ferrante, Patrick Gorman, Vance Hartke, Reverend Joseph Lamanno, Frank Mercurio, Edward A. Nyegaard, Austin H. Perlow, John Scheier, Charles E. Sinnegan, Sam Talarico, Joseph Tuvim, Leo F. Zeller.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically and topically.
Organized into 7 series:
I, New York State Convention
II, Annual Labor-Management Show
III, Union Label Week
IV, Miss Union Maid
V, Chronological
VI, Miscellaneous Subjects
VII, Work Sites
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Records (Wagner 54); (Photographs 024) (lantern slides with union label emblems).
American Federation of Labor. Bookkeepers, Stenographers and Accountants Union.; Archer, Alexander; Avrutin, Harry; Becker, Isidore--Portraits.; Carey, Phillip A.--Portraits.; Cleary, Edward J. (Edward John), 1906-; Diggs, Bertha J.--Portraits.; Ferrante, Nicholas--Portraits.; Gorman, Patrick Emmet, 1892-1980; Hartke, Vance--Portraits.; Lamanno, (Reverend) Joseph --Portraits.; Mercurio, Frank--Portraits.; Nyegaard, Edward A.--Portraits.; Perlow, Austin H.--Portraits.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Santiago Igelesias Educational Society.; Scheier, John--Portraits.; Sinnegan, Charles E.--Portraits.; Talarico, Sam--Portraits.; Tuvim, Joseph--Portraits.; Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island. -- |v Pictorial works; Zeller, Leo F.--Portraits.; Beauty contests |v Pictorial works.; Black-and-white photographs.; Butchers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Portraits.; Congresses and conventions |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Disabled persons |v Portraits.; Glaziers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Portraits.; Labor leaders |z New York (State) |z New York |v Portraits.; Labor union meetings |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Labor unions |x Butchers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.
- Series I: New York State Annual Convention
  - Union Label Trades and Services Department – NYS Convention, Rochester, 1942 (Folder 1)
  - 29th Annual Convention (and 3rd Labor-Management Exhibit), 1956 (Folder 2)
  - 30th Convention and 5th Labor-Management Show – Clippings, 1957 (Folder 3)
  - 30th Department Convention, Labor-Management Show, 1957 (Folder 4)
  - 31st Annual Convention, [1958] (Folder 5)
  - 32nd Annual Convention – Clippings, 1959 (Folder 6)
  - 32nd Annual Convention, 5th Empire State Labor-Management Show, 1959 (Folder 7)
  - 33rd Convention, Utica, 1960 (Folder 8)
  - 34th Convention, Jamestown, 1961 (Folder 9)
  - 35th Annual Convention – Clippings, 1962 (Folder 10)
  - 35th Annual Convention, Rochester (#1 of 3 folders), 1962 (Folder 11)
  - 35th Annual Convention, Rochester (#2 of 3 folders), 1962 (Folder 12)
  - 35th Annual Convention, Rochester (#3 of 3 folders), 1962 (Folder 13)
  - 36th Annual Convention, Syracuse, [1963] (Folder 14)
  - 37th Convention, NYC, Statler Hotel, [1964] (Folder 15)
  - 38th Convention, Buffalo, 1965 (Folder 16)
  - 11th Show Pix/Buffalo, 1965 (Folder 17)
  - 39th Convention, Utica, NY, [1966] (Folder 18)
  - 40th Convention, Rochester, 1967 (Folder 19)
  - 41st Convention, Albany, NY, Thruway Motor Inn, 1968 (Folder 20)
  - 42nd Convention, Syracuse, NY, [1969] (Folder 21)
  - 43rd Convention, Albany, 1970 (Folder 22)
  - 46th Union Label Convention, 1973 (Folder 23)
- Series II: Annual Labor-Management Show
  - Union Label Exhibit (State), Utica, 1954 (Folder 24)
  - Union Industry Show, 4th, 1957 (Folder 25)
  - 8th Annual Labor/Management Show - Clippings, 1959 (Folder 26)
  - 8th Empire State Labor-Management Exhibit, 1962 (Folder 27)
  - Labor-Management Show – Clippings, 1963 (Folder 28)
  - 9th Empire State Labor-Management Show Exhibit, Statler Hilton, NYC, 1963 (Folder 29)
  - 9th Labor and Management Exhibit, Syracuse, 1963 (Folder 30)
  - Probably Labor and Management Exhibit NYC, 1963 (Folder 31)
  - 10th Labor-Management Exhibit, 1964 (Folder 32)
  - 1965 Show – NYC 11th (Folder 33)
  - 12th Annual, Roosevelt Raceway, 1966 (Folder 34)
  - 1967 Exhibit, PCE Show Promos, Garden City (13th Annual Exhibit) (Folder 35)
  - 13th Labor and Management Exhibit – probably 1967 Labor and Management Exhibit or Planning (Folder 36)
  - 14th Labor and Management Exhibit, Rochester, 1968 (Folder 37)
  - 15th Labor and Management Exhibit / NYC, 1969 (Folder 38)
  - 16th Labor and Management Exhibit, Albany, 1970 (Folder 39)
  - 17th Labor and Management Exhibit, 1971 (Folder 40)
  - 18th Labor and Management Exhibit, 1972 (Folder 41)
  - Labor-Management Show – Clippings, 1973 (Folder 42)
  - 19th Labor and Management Exhibit, 1973 (Folder 43)
- Series III: Union Label Week
  - Union Label Week w/ Mayor Impelliteri at 45 Astor Place, Sep 2, 1951 (Folder 44)
  - Union Label Week, NYC w/ Mayor Wagner, 1954 (Folder 45)
  - Union Label Week, incl. NYS governor’s and NYC mayor’s proclamations, 1957 (Folder 46)
  - Union Label Week – Clippings, 1959 (Folder 47)
  - Union Label Week, 1950s (Folder 48)
  - Union Label Week, 1966 (Folder 49)
  - Union Label Week, 1967 (Folder 50)
  - Union Label Week, [1967] (Folder 51)
  - Union Label Week, 1969 (Folder 52)
  - Union Label Week, 1970 (Folder 53)
  - Union Label Week, 1971 (Folder 54)
  - Union Label Week, 1972 (Folder 55)
  - Union Label Week – Rochester, 1973 (Folder 56)
  - Union Label Week, 1976, 1974, undated (Folder 57)
- Series IV: Miss Union Maid
  - Miss Union Maid Contestants, 1959 (Folder 58)
  - Miss Union Maid, undated (Folder 59)
  - Miss Union Maid [4 x 5 Prints], undated (Folder 60)
- Series V: Chronological
  - 1910s, 1910-1919 (Folder 61)
  - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Folder 62)
  - 1930s ?, [1930-1939] (Folder 63)
  - Charles Sinnigen, ca.1930-1949 (Folder 64)
  - Early photos w/ C. Sinnigen, 1940-1949 (Folder 65)
  - 1940s, 1940-1949 (Folder 65.1)
  - 1940s ?, [1940-1949] (Folder 66)
  - 1950 (Folder 67)
  - 1951 (Folder 68)
  - 1952 (Folder 69)
  - 1953 (Folder 70)
  - 1954 (Folder 71)
  - 1956 (Folder 73)
  - 1957-58, 1957-1958 (Folder 74)
  - 1958 (Folder 75)
  - 1959 (Folder 76)
  - Informational Picket, Department Stores Against Imports, NYC, early 1950s, 1950-1955 (Folder 77)
  - 1950s ? (1 of 2), [1950-1959] (Folder 78)
  - 1950s ? (1 of 2), [1950-1959] (Folder 79)
  - New York and Long Island Union Label Luncheon – Reverend Phillip A. Carey, 1962 (Folder 80)
  - 1963 (Folder 81)
  - Union Label Services and Trades – National Convention, 51st Convention/Nat. Union Label Trades and Services Department, NYC, 1963 (Folder 82)
  - 1964 (Folder 83)
  - 1964 – Union Label Award of Merit (Folder 84)
  - 1966 (Folder 85)
  - Greater New York and Long Island Union Label, Fleisher - Award of Merit, 1966 (Folder 86)
  - fr. Long Island Union Label Award of Merit, 1966-1967 (Folder 87)
  - Rheingold Brewers/ OPEIU ’53 Contract Celebration, 1966 (Folder 88)
  - 1967 (Folder 89)
  - 6th – greater New York and Long Island Union Label, Commodore Hotel, NYC, Hickey Perry, Sep 6, 1967 (Folder 90)
  - 6th Long Island and NY Union Label Luncheon, Perry, Hickey; Long Island Luncheon Union Label; 2nd Award of Merit, Sep 6, 1967, Sep 8, 1967 (Folder 91)
  - #1049 Award presentation, Oct 4, 1967 (Folder 92)
  - Expo ‘67, 1967 (Folder 93)
  - 1968 (Folder 94)
  - New York and Long Island Union Label Luncheon, 1968 (Folder 95)
  - 3rd – Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, De Konig, Regnell, 1968 (Folder 96)
  - 1969 (Folder 97)
  - Pictures from Demonstration Arts Project File, 1969, undated (Folder 98)
  - 8th – Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, Commodore Hotel, NYC. R. Booth, J. Townsend – Awards, Sep 10, 1969 (Folder 99)
  - 1960s ? (Folder 100)
  - 1970 (Folder 101)
  - 9th – Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, NYC, Sep 9, 1970 (Folder 102)
  - Long Island Union Label, Garden City, Long Island Epstein, Favale, Sep 11, 1970 (Folder 103)
  - 1971 (Folder 104)
  - Labor Journalism Award, 1971 (Folder 105)
  - 60th Anniversary Dinner/1971, Greater New York and Long Island Union Label (Folder 106)
  - 1972 (Folder 107)
  - Award of Merit Dinner, Arthur L. Harckham, recipient, 1972 (Folder 108)
  - 10th Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, Commodore Hotel, NYC. Hect, Glick, Sep 13, 1972 (Folder 109)
  - 6th – Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, Hempstead, Long Island. Caso, Gamaldi., Sep 22, 1972 (Folder 110)
  - 1973, 1973, Sep 19, 1973 (Folder 111)
  - Farah – Trip to El Paso, Sep 1, 1973 (Folder 112)
  - Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, Commodore Hotel, NYC, Local 100, TWU, Sep 9, 1973 (Folder 113)
  - 1974 (Folder 114)
  - Austin Perlow – Retirement Party, 1974 (Folder 115)
  - Conference at UIIC, 6/17/74 by Upholsterers’ Association of Met. District, 17-Jun (Folder 116)
  - Greater NY and Long Island Union Label, Commodore Hotel, NYC, Sep 25, 1974 (Folder 117)
  - 1975 (Folder 118)
  - Union Label Pace at Roosevelt, Patrick J. Gleason Award of Merit, Apr 2, 1975 (Folder 119)
  - 13th Greater NY Union Label Luncheon, 1975 (Folder 120)
  - 1976 (Folder 121)
  - NYC AFL-CIO Convention, 1976 (Folder 122)
  - NYS UNION LABEL TRADES AND SERVICES DEPARTMENT Union Label Pace at Roosevelt, F. Tooze, C. Hopple/ Awards of Merit, Jan 21, 1976 (Folder 123)
  - Reception for Sam Talarico/ Earl D. McDavid, Talarico Leaving, Sep 27, 1976 (Folder 124)
  - 1970s ? (1 of 2 ), [1970-1979] (Folder 125)
  - 1970s ? (2 of 2), [1970-1979] (Folder 126)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous Subjects
  - fr. Burker-Hartke Rally Folder, undated (Folder 127)
  - Concert, undated (Folder 128)
  - Consumer Assembly, undated (Folder 129)
  - Demonstration Against Imports – Alexander’s, undated (Folder 130)
  - Grape Boycott, undated (Folder 131)
  - Labor Day Parade, 1968 (Folder 132)
  - Labor Day Parade (NPA95-18), 1959-1961 (Folder 133)
  - Labor Day Parade (NPA95-18), 1981-1983 (Folder 134)
  - John Baer cartoon, undated (Folder 135)
  - Portraits, undated (Folder 136)
  - Lil’ Miss Union Maid, Pete the Pup, undated (Folder 137)
  - Montages – Misc. (pics, reprints), undated (Folder 138)
  - Farah Boycott – Adopt a Family, undated (Folder 139)
  - Rupperts Luncheon, undated (Folder 140)
  - Santiago Iglesias Educational Society, undated (Folder 141)
  - UUC (Union Industries Information Center), undated (Folder 142)
  - UUC Pix, NCR, undated (Folder 143)
  - The Union Shopper, undated (Folder 144)
- Series VII: Worksites
  - Bottling Assembly Line, undated (Folder 145)
  - Glazier Series, for Industrial Bulletin Article, 1968 (Folder 146)
  - Hotel ? Cooks and Wait Staff, undated (Folder 147)
  - Meat packing plant work shots, undated (Folder 148)